Hugh Johnston fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Hugh Johnston fonds
1958 - 2004
F-223
Q104445042
2.38 m of textual records 72 sound recordings
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Johnston, Hugh
Hugh Johnston is professor emeritus of history at Simon Fraser University, where he taught for 37 years. His book Radical Campus: Making Simon Fraser University was published to coincide with the university's 40th anniversary (2005). He joined SFU as a faculty member in 1968 and witnessed firsthand SFU's tumultuous beginnings. At various times in his career, Johnston led the History Department as chair.
Johnston grew up in south-western Ontario. He received a B.A. from the University of Toronto and attended the Ontario College of Education. Johnston went on to receive an M.A. from the University of Western Ontario and his PhD. from King's College at the University of London.
His teaching and research interests have centered on British and South Asian migration and settlement, eighteenth century exploration of the Pacific Northwest, the history of British Columbia, and higher education in Canada. Johnston is well known as an expert in Sikhism, Sikhs in Canada, and India-China relations. From 1992 to 2001 he also served on the board of the Shastri Indo-Canadian Institute, a bi-national organization promoting scholarly exchange, and in 1995–1996 he was resident director of the institute's office in Delhi. In 2001 he was the institute's president.
During his career, Johnston wrote numerous scholarly articles and books. In 1995, with Tara Singh Bains he co-wrote The Four Quarters of the Night: The Life Journey of an Emmigrant Sikh. Other books include The Voyage of the Komagata Maru: The Sikh Challenge to Canada's Colour Bar; British Immigration Policy, 1815-1830: "Shovelling out Paupers"; and the History of Perth County to 1967 (co-authored with W. Stafford Johnston).
published
Full
Revised
The title of the fonds is based on the name of the records creator.
41 sound recordings are contained on 69 audio cassettes.
Fonds consists of research material gathered by Johnston for his book Radical Campus: Making Simon Fraser University. Subjects, events and activities documented include the socio-political context of post-secondary education in the 1960s; the establishment of SFU; and the rise of student activism. The fonds consists primarily of photocopied material from fonds and newspapers; interview transcriptions and audiocassettes; and notes and drafts.
The archivist arranged most of the materials based upon a classification provided by Hugh Johnston. Variations are noted in the series and sub-series descriptions.
Sound recordings; Textual records; Education; Burnaby
The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by Hugh Johnston in 2006.
Further accruals are expected.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Series, sub-series, and sub-sub-series descriptions and file lists are available. An item list has been produced for the audiocassettes in sub-series 7. Hugh Johnston created indices of the material he compiled and they are included in Appendix B (hard copy version of the finding aid only, available in the Archives Reading Room). He also created two other indices in a yellow notebook; one for photocopied issues of The Peak and the other for photocopied fonds material. The notebook can be found in F-223-1-2-3.
- Radical Campus files, 1958 - 2004; F-223-1; 2.55 m of textual records 72 sound recordings; Date range: Predominant dates of textual material in the series are 1965-1974. General note: sound recordings are located in series F-223-1-7-2.
  published
  Series consists of research material gathered by Hugh Johnston for his book Radical Campus: Making Simon Fraser University. Radical Campus was published to coincide with the university's 40th anniversary in 2005. Subjects, events and activities documented include the socio-political context of post-secondary education in the 1960s; the establishment of SFU; the rise of student activism; the growth of academic departments and faculties; the role of prominent members of the SFU community; and the governance and administration of SFU. Series includes photocopied newspaper articles; photocopied fonds material such as correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, press releases, briefs, bulletins, book excerpts, drafts, curriculum vitae, interview transcriptions; working papers; audiocassette recordings; chapter drafts; and indices.
  The arrangement of the series into sub-series and sub-sub-series are based on the original filing system of the creator. The arrangement of sub-series 5 (Miscellaneous material - C.R. Day) and sub-series 6 (Miscellaneous material - Steve Hicks) into files was provided by the archvist as no order was apparent.
  Hicks, Steve; Sound recordings
  Further accruals to the series are expected.
  The series consists primarily of material collected by Hugh Johnston; however it also contains material collected during an earlier attempt at writing the history of SFU. In 1990 President William Saywell commissioned history professor Robin Fisher to undertake a history of SFU. Fisher hired graduate student Steve Hicks as his research assistant to photocopy background material from the SFU Archives. When Fisher accepted a position at the University of Northern British Columbia, he took the photocopied material with him. Other commitments forced Fisher to abandon the SFU history project.
  When a new SFU President, Michael Stevenson, asked Hugh Johnston, to write the history of SFU, Johnston contacted Robin Fisher who sent him his photocopied material in 2001. Johnston incorporated this material into his own records. The Fisher-Hicks material is recognizable because of the "RG" (record group) notation by Hicks at the top of each photocopied document. In 2004, Hicks sent Johnston additional photocopied material that had been forgotten in the basement of his parents' house. The archivist did not retain this material except for draft chapters and notes.
  - Background material - Chapters 1, 2 and 3, 1958 - 2004; F-223-1-1; 1.11 m of textual records
    Sub-series consists primarily of photocopied background material, which Hugh Johnston used as sources for chapters one, two and three in Radical Campus. Subjects, events and activities documented include the socio-political context of post-secondary education in the 1960s; the establishment of SFU; prominent members of the SFU community; student activism; and university disputes. Sub-series includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes, newspaper articles, reports, press releases, journal and magazine articles, working papers, bulletins, drafts, book excerpts, and discussion papers.
    - Chronological and topical subject files, 1963 - 1975; F-223-1-1-1; 35 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists primarily of photocopied material from the Sun, the Province, the Peak, the Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT) Bulletin, and other publications relating to the development of SFU. Subjects, events and activities documented include post-secondary education in the 1960s; student activism; the development and administration of SFU; post-secondary educational systems; faculty-administration relations; the Board of Governors; the CAUT Censure; the PSA affair; the Shell service station dispute; and the presidencies of Patrick McTaggart-Cowan and Kenneth Strand. Records include journal and magazine articles; newspaper clippings; reports and book excerpts.
      Strand, Kenneth; Canadian Association of University Teachers; McTaggart-Cowan, Patrick; Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology
      - General material, 1963; F-223-1-1-1-1 (Archival box - standard 223-1)
        Textual records
        Pending review
      - President McTaggart-Cowan, 1963 - 1964; F-223-1-1-1-2 (Archival box - standard 223-1)
      - General material, January 1964 - June 1964; F-223-1-1-1-3 (Archival box - standard 223-1)
      - General material, July 1964 - December 1964; F-223-1-1-1-4 (Archival box - standard 223-1)
      - General material, 1965 - 1966; F-223-1-1-1-5 (Archival box - standard 223-1)
        Open
      - Fisher material: Shell gas station dispute, 1966; F-223-1-1-1-6 (Archival box - standard 223-1)
        Open with enclosures
        Reviewed for access (Dec 5, 2023) – The bulk of the file is open. However, it includes a small number of documents (4) that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (employment history, educational history). Restricted documents have been removed (enclosed); the rest of the file is open. Enclosed records may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
      - Newspaper articles, 1967; F-223-1-1-1-7 (Archival box - standard 223-1)
      - Teaching assistant affair, 1967; F-223-1-1-1-8 (Archival box - standard 223-1)
        Restricted in part
      - Fisher material: general, 1967; F-223-1-1-1-9 (Archival box - standard 223-2)
      - General material, January 1968 - June 1968; F-223-1-1-1-10 (Archival box - standard 223-2)
      - Andre Gunder Frank, 1968; F-223-1-1-1-11 (Archival box - standard 223-2)
        Frank, Andre Gunder; Textual records
      - General material, July 1968 - December 1968; F-223-1-1-1-12 (Archival box - standard 223-2)
      - Fisher material: general, 1969; F-223-1-1-1-13 (Archival box - standard 223-2)
      - Fisher material: general, 1970 - 1971; F-223-1-1-1-14 (Archival box - standard 223-2)
      - The Perry Report - finances, 1972; F-223-1-1-1-15 (Archival box - standard 223-2)
      - Strand papers #1, 1968 - 1974; F-223-1-1-1-16 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
      - Strand papers #2, 1969 - 1973; F-223-1-1-1-17 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
      - Academic Vice-President papers, 1968 - 1975; F-223-1-1-1-18 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
      - Senate papers, 1973 - 1974; F-223-1-1-1-19 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
      - Senate: open session/closed session, 1968 - 1969; F-223-1-1-1-20 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
      - Board of Govenors papers, 1968 - 1974; F-223-1-1-1-21 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
      - Academic Planning Committee, 1969 - 1975; F-223-1-1-1-22 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
        Academic Planning Committee; Textual records
      - Continuing Committee on the Status of Women, 1975; F-223-1-1-1-23 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
      - Canadian Association of University Teachers' censure, 1968; F-223-1-1-1-24 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
    - Publications, 1958 - 1999; F-223-1-1-2; 18 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists primarily of photocopied material from the Sun, the Province, the Peak, the Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT) Bulletin, and other publications relating to the development of SFU. Subjects, events and activities documented include post-secondary education in the 1960s; student activism; Chancellor Gordon Shrum; the development and administration of SFU; post-secondary educational systems; faculty-administration relations; the Board of Governors; the CAUT Censure; the PSA affair; the Shell service station dispute; and the presidency of Kenneth Strand. Records include journal and magazine articles; newspaper clippings; reports and book excerpts.
      Shrum, Gordon; Board of Governors; Canadian Association of University Teachers; Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; Strand, Kenneth
      - Newspaper articles, 1963 - 1966; F-223-1-1-2-1 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
      - Newspaper and magazine articles, 1966; F-223-1-1-2-2 (Archival box - standard 223-3)
      - Newspaper clippings, vol. 1, 1968; F-223-1-1-2-3 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - Newspaper clippings, vol. 2, 1968; F-223-1-1-2-4 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1969 - 1972; F-223-1-1-2-5 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - From instant university to academic disaster…, [Saturday Night article], 1971; F-223-1-1-2-6 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - Canadian Association of University Teachers bulletins, vol. 1, 1960 - 1965; F-223-1-1-2-7 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - Canadian Association of University Teachers bulletins, vol. 2, 1965 - 1968; F-223-1-1-2-8 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - Canadian Dimension articles, 1963 - 1968; F-223-1-1-2-9 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - MacLean's articles, 1967 - 1968; F-223-1-1-2-10 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - Annual Report, 1966 - 1967; F-223-1-1-2-11 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1968 - 1985; F-223-1-1-2-12 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - Bibliography of published articles on SFU, 1975; F-223-1-1-2-13 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - Chapter 2 reference material, 1958 - 1968; F-223-1-1-2-14 (Archival box - standard 223-4)
      - SFU Alumni journal, 1990; F-223-1-1-2-15 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
      - Articles on education, 1962 - 1999; F-223-1-1-2-16 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
      - Georgia Strait articles, 1968 - 1970; F-223-1-1-2-17 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
      - Bridge articles and a PSA working paper, 1969 - 1971; F-223-1-1-2-18 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
      - Our Generation articles, 1961 - 1971; F-223-1-1-2-19 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
      - Sixites publications/Georgia Strait articles, 1968 - 1970; F-223-1-1-2-20 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
    - Files on individuals, 1961 - 2004; F-223-1-1-3; 34 cm of textual records; See access points below for a list of individuals.
      Sub-sub-series consists primarily of photocopied material on prominent members of the SFU community including administrators, faculty and students (for list, see "Access points"). Subjects, events and activities documented include academic freedom; academic planning; the PSA affair; faculty associations; recruitment of department heads; faculty appointments and the Teaching Assistants affair. Sub-sub-series contains a diary of the daily activities of George Suart, appointed as SFU’s first Vice-President for Administration in 1968. Sub-sub-series also contains memoranda; reports; bulletins; cartoons; correspondence; printed emails; interview transcriptions; magazine and newspaper articles; working papers; and curriculum vitae.
      - Aberle, Kathleen Gough, 1967 - 2001; F-223-1-1-3-1 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Aberle, Kathleen; Textual records
      - Adam, Heribert, 1975 - 2004; F-223-1-1-3-2 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Adam, Heribert; Textual records
      - Baker, Ron, 1962 - 2003; F-223-1-1-3-3 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Baker, Ron; Textual records
      - Baker, Ron - documents, 1964 - 2004; F-223-1-1-3-4 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
      - Blaney, Jack P., 1995 - 2001; F-223-1-1-3-5 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Blaney, Jack P.; Textual records
      - Bottomore, Tom B., 1967 - 2003; F-223-1-1-3-6 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Bottomore, Tom B.; Textual records
      - Briemberg, Mordecai, 1970; F-223-1-1-3-7 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Briemberg, Mordecai; Textual records
      - Bursill-Hall, Geoffrey, 1998; F-223-1-1-3-8 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Bursill-Hall, Geoffrey L.; Textual records
      - Caple, Kenneth, 1980 - [198-?]; F-223-1-1-3-9 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Caple, Kenneth P.; Textual records
      - Copes, Parzival, 1969 - 1975; F-223-1-1-3-10 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Copes, Parzival; Textual records
      - Curtis, George F., 1963 - 2001; F-223-1-1-3-11 (Archival box - standard 223-5)
        Curtis, George F.; Textual records
      - Daniells, Roy, 2002; F-223-1-1-3-12 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        File consists of a photocopy of an excerpt from Sandra Djwa's book, "Professing English: A Life of Roy Daniells."
        Daniells, Roy; Djwa, Sandra; Textual records
      - Day, C.R., 2001; F-223-1-1-3-13 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Day, C.R.; Textual records
      - Diamond, Jack, 2001; F-223-1-1-3-14 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Diamond, Jack; Textual records
      - Duguid, Steven, 1968 - 2002; F-223-1-1-3-15 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Duguid, Steve; Textual records
      - Ellis, John, 1969; F-223-1-1-3-16 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Ellis, John F.; Textual records
      - Erickson, Arthur, 1972 - 2001; F-223-1-1-3-17 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Erickson, Arthur; Textual records
      - Evans, Harry M., 2002; F-223-1-1-3-18 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Evans, Harry M.; Textual records
      - Evenden, Leonard J., 2002; F-223-1-1-3-19 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Evenden, Len; Textual records
      - Gee, Ellen, 2002; F-223-1-1-3-20 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Gee, Ellen M.; Textual records
      - Hamilton, Charles L., 1966 - 1971; F-223-1-1-3-21 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Hamilton, Charles L.; Textual records
      - Jennings, Ray, 2002; F-223-1-1-3-22 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Jennings, Ray E.; Textual records
      - Jewett, Pauline, 1974 - 1978; F-223-1-1-3-23 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Jewett, Pauline; Textual records
      - Jewett papers, 1974 - 1977; F-223-1-1-3-24 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
      - Lambert, Ruth, 2001; F-223-1-1-3-25 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Lambert, Ruth; Textual records
      - Lebowitz, Michael, 2002; F-223-1-1-3-26 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Lebowitz, Michael; Textual records
      - Leggett, John C., 1966 - 1970; F-223-1-1-3-27 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Leggett, John C.; Textual records
      - Loney, Martin, 1968 - 2002; F-223-1-1-3-28 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Loney, Martin; Textual records
      - MacKinnon, Archie, 1964 - 1965; F-223-1-1-3-29 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        MacKinnon, Archie R.; Textual records
      - Maud, Ralph, 2001; F-223-1-1-3-30 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Maud, Ralph; Textual records
      - McTaggart-Cowan, Patrick, 1961 - 1998; F-223-1-1-3-31 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        McTaggart-Cowan, Patrick; Textual records
      - McTaggart-Cowan interview, 1986; F-223-1-1-3-32 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
      - Maier, Derek, 2000; F-223-1-1-3-33 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Maier, Derek; Textual records
      - Mills, John, 1984; F-223-1-1-3-34 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Mills, John; Textual records
      - Mitchell, David, 1998; F-223-1-1-3-35 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Mitchell, David; Textual records
      - Munro, Jock, 1968 - 2001; F-223-1-1-3-36 (Archival box - standard 223-6)
        Munro, John M.; Textual records
      - Noble, David, 2001 - 2002; F-223-1-1-3-37 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Noble, David; Textual records
      - Okuda, Kenji, 2002; F-223-1-1-3-38 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Okuda, Kenji; Textual records
      - Rieckhoff, Klaus, 1982 - 1997; F-223-1-1-3-39 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Rieckhoff, Klaus E.; Textual records
      - Saywell, William, 1987; F-223-1-1-3-40 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Saywell, William George; Textual records
      - Shrum, Gordon, 1968 - 1985; F-223-1-1-3-41 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Shrum, Gordon; Textual records
      - Shrum, Gordon - impressions and recollections of, 1985; F-223-1-1-3-42 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
      - Sharma, Hari, 2002; F-223-1-1-3-43 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Sharma, Hari; Textual records
      - Stevenson, Michael, 2001; F-223-1-1-3-44 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Stevenson, Michael; Textual records
      - Strand, Kenneth, 1972; F-223-1-1-3-45 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Strand, Kenneth; Textual records
      - Strand, Kenneth - interview notes, 2000; F-223-1-1-3-46 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
      - Strand, Kenneth - original photograph and cartoons, [197-?]; F-223-1-1-3-47 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
      - Strand, Kenneth - speeches and letters, 1968 - 1974; F-223-1-1-3-48 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
      - Suart, George - diary excerpts, 1968 - 1975; F-223-1-1-3-49 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Suart, George; Textual records
      - Swartz, Norman, 1998 - 2002; F-223-1-1-3-50 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Swartz, Norman; Textual records
      - Taylor, Chris, 2001 - 2002; F-223-1-1-3-51 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Taylor, Chris; Textual records
      - Tietz, John, [198-?] - 2002; F-223-1-1-3-52 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Tietz, John H.; Textual records
      - Wickstrom, Norman - "The PSA dispute at SFU", 1974; F-223-1-1-3-53 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Wickstrom, Norman; Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; Textual records
      - Wilson, Brian, 1973 - 1983; F-223-1-1-3-54 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Wilson, Brian G.; Textual records
      - Wilson, Letty, 1971 - 1993; F-223-1-1-3-55 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Wilson, Lolita; Textual records
      - Wong, Milton, 2002; F-223-1-1-3-56 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Wong, Milton K.; Textual records
      - Wong, Stan, 1969; F-223-1-1-3-57 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Wong, Stan; Textual records
      - Wylie, Robert, 2002; F-223-1-1-3-58 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Wylie, Robert; Textual records
      - Yandle, Sharon, 1970 - 2002; F-223-1-1-3-59 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Yandle, Sharon; Textual records
      - Zaslove, Jerry, 2002; F-223-1-1-3-60 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Zaslove, Jerald; Textual records
      - Vidaver, Bill, 1980; F-223-1-1-3-61 (Archival box - standard 223-7)
        Vidaver, Bill; Textual records
    - Files on subjects, 1962 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4; 23 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists primarily of photocopied material relating to the history of Simon Fraser University. Subjects, events and activities documented include academic planning; academic freedom, tenure and promotion; student activism; student and faculty affairs; faculty-administration relations; the crisis in post-secondary education; the PSA affair; the development of several academic departments; the development of the Teaching Support Staff Union (TSSU); the trimester system; and the overall growth and expansion of the university and its programs. Sub-sub-series includes memoranda; newspaper articles; minutes; discussion papers; printed emails; correspondence; journal articles; book excerpts; reports; annual reports; statistics; working papers; and an honors essay.
      Teaching Support Staff Union; Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology
      - Academic Freedom, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4-1 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
      - Academic Planner, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4-2 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        File consists of handwritten notes summarizing the contents of documents in held in SFU Archives in the Academic Planning Office fonds (F-49).
        Academic Planning Office; Textual records
      - Burnaby Mountain Development Corporation, 1998; F-223-1-1-4-3 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        SFU Community Trust; Textual records
      - Business Faculty, 1996; F-223-1-1-4-4 (Archival box - standard 223-8)